Guide to the Hollon Augustine Farr Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Hollon Augustine Farr papers
1604-1956
MS 910
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.5
Correspondence, reports, and miscellaneous materials largely related to Farr's administrative work and his teaching in the Department of Germanic Languages at Yale University. Also included is his autograph collection and a report from Georg Kartzke, former member of the Yale Department, on conditions at the University of Berlin between 1939 and 1946.
Farr, Hollon Augustine, 1872-1958
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Hollon Farr between 1941 and 1954.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Hollon A. Farr Papers consist of personal materials related to Farr's teaching and administrative career at Yale and autograph letters, documents and other items collected by him.
The personal materials consist of correspondence; notebooks from his undergraduate years; teaching and administrative materials such as grade books, student lists, examination and meeting reports; and miscellaneous items including photographs, notes, and reports by Georg Kartzke, a former professor of German at Yale, on conditions at the University of Berlin between 1939 and 1946.
The autograph letters, documents and other collected items span mainly from the mid-eighteenth to the mid-nineteenth century. However, some items date from the seventeenth and twentieth centuries. The material concerns American and European persons and places. It is arranged alphabetically and cataloged individually in the department's manuscript catalog.
The Hollon A. Farr papers were given to Yale University Library by Hollon Farr between 1941 and 1954.
Biographical / Historical
Hollon A. Farr, 1872-1958
Assistant professor of German, Yale University, New Haven
Hollon Augustine Farr was born at Athol, Mass., on September 2, 1872, the son of Hollon Farr and Mary Wheeler, and a descendant of early Massachusetts settlers. Charles E. Farr, '98, M.D. '03, is a brother.
Farr came to college from Andover. He had a philosophical oration at the Junior Exhibition and at Commencement, and received the Scott German Prize, two-year honors in ancient languages, and an election to Phi Beta Kappa. He was a member of Zeta Psi.
He studied in Germany after graduation, and in 1898 took up his work at Yale as tutor in German, and has continued as instructor and assistant professor, besides assuming many administrative duties. Yale gave him an M.A. in 1902 and a Ph.D. in 1904. In 1906 he was made chairman of the Freshman faculty.
From 1911-1920, inclusive, he was chairman of the Freshman faculty in Yale College. From 1914 to 1919, he was also chairman of the College committee on Admissions, and as such was brought in pleasant contact with many preparatory schools, and also with Harvard and Princeton. With the reorganization of the University both of these offices passed from the college to the University, and in 1920-1921 he became chairman of the Sophomore faculty in Yale College. He also performed the duties of registrar of the College for a year when someone was on sabbatical. For 1921-1922 he took a leave of absence, and returned to the College in October, 1922, with no other duties than that of a teacher of German. He served as a fellow of Trumbull College from 1933-1939 and then was an associate fellow from 1939 to his death. He was a curator of Yale Memorabilia at the University library from 1940 to his death. He was a professor emeritus from 1929 onwards.
During the war Farr taught classes in the Yale R.O.T.C. and S.A.T.C. from September, 1917, to December 1918, and served (under Jack Adams) as Permanent Officer of the Day at the Yale R.O.T.C. Summer Camp in 1918. He also collaborated with Professor Hewitt of Williams College in issuing a small manual called "German for the American Soldiers." He was a Republican,—"mainly," he says—belonging to the Graduates and the New Haven Country clubs in New Haven, and to the Zeta Psi Club of New York. He was not married.
Autographs; Educators; Farr, Hollon Augustine, 1872-1958; Kartzke, Georg; Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Officals and employees; Yale University. Department of Germanic Languages
- Inventory
  - Personal papers
    - Correspondence
      - A-Me, 1906-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Mi-Z, 1905-1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Notes on the Bible, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Notebook on German history and phonetics, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Grade books, 1898-1911, 1921-1923 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Class lists and course lists, 1898-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Examinations, grade lists and student lists, 1901-1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Contract for the rental of the Hyperion Theater, New Haven, Connecticut, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Reports and minutes, statistics and miscellaneous administrative materials, 1923, 1931-1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Appointment books, 1927, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Translation by Farr re: the Karajan family, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous printed matter in German, 1928, 1929, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Georg Kartzke, reports re: conditions at the University of Berlin since 1939, 1946 Jan, September (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Lists of military terms, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Memorabilia, 1896-1939 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - [Howard Wadsworth Church?]: notebook containing photographs and humorous text, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Newspaper clipping, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous notes, [1892?], 1922, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Collection (A-Z), 1743-1925 (Box 3)
  - Oversize, 1604-1940 (Box 4)